Guide to the Amos Burg Photographs 1889-1986
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Amos Burg photographs
1889-1985
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Org. Lot 450
Burg, Amos
Approx. 7 cubic feet 14,187 photographs, 9,244 negatives, 7,791 slides, 28 lantern slides, and 70 photomechanical prints in 18 boxes plus other unprocessed additions
Images document Amos Burg's world travels, explorations, and river running, as well as his careers as a writer, photographer and filmmaker for National Geographic, Encyclopaedia Britannica, and ERPI Classroom Films, and his work with the Alaska Fish and Game Department.
Biographical Note
Amos Burg (1901-1986) was born in Portland, Or., to Amos Burg, Sr., and Minerva Ann James Burg (Annie Laurie Burg). Burg, Sr. (1863-1938), immigrated from Norway in 1877 to Council Bluffs, Iowa, where he worked in the laundry business and married Minerva Ann James in 1889. They and their infant son, Charles, moved to Portland in 1890, and the senior Burg became part owner of the City Laundry. In Portland, the couple had seven more children, including Amos, Jr. The Burgs' longtime family home at 1706 N.E. Dekum Avenue was still standing as of 2004.
Upon graduation from grammar school in June 1917, Burg persuaded his parents to let him go to sea as bell boy on the passenger ship, Rose City, Portland to San Francisco and Los Angeles. At the end of the summer, he returned to Portland to start high school but the call of the sea was so strong that he returned to sea, where during many voyages in the next several years, he continued his education using the Encyclopaedia Britannica. This whetted his appetite for more learning, so between voyages, he completed a college preparatory course at the Oregon Institute of Technology and then enrolled in science, photography, and journalism courses at the University of Oregon (Eugene) and Oregon State College (now Oregon State University, Corvallis) between adventures (1926-1929), although he never earned a degree. He helped to finance his education and adventures by using his sea voyages as an opportunity to earn some money importing Oriental rug, silks, and pearls.
Burg was heralded for making the first complete canoe voyage on the Columbia River from its headwaters in Columbia Lake, B.C., to the Pacific Oct. 20, 1924-Jan. 7, 1925. The newspapers followed his adventure, and this voyage started his lecture career, as he became a sought-after speaker in Portland and elsewhere in western Oregon. By 1930, he was becoming a successsful lecturer on the national circuit with tales of his adventures, illustrated with his own films and slides, accompanied by narration in his self-depracating witty style. Burg followed up his Columbia River triumph in the summer of 1925 with a canoe voyage from the headwaters of the Snake River at Jackson Lake, Wyo., through Hells Canyon, and down the Columbia River to its mouth. At the Cascades of the Columbia (site of the Bonneville Dam in 2004), Fox Movietone and International Newsreel cameramen persuaded Burg to run the cascades in his canoe, which resulted in International newsreel headlines, "Amos Burg first man to attempt passage of swirling Columbia waters in frail craft." Well into the 1930s, Burg continued to make periodic canoe trips on the Columbia, Snake, Yukon and Northwest Territories rivers, culminating in his 1938 trip to film Buzz Holmstrom's re-creation of his 1937 one-man trip down the Green and Colorado rivers. Burg took the first inflatable rubber raft down the Colorado on this trip, and his film, Conquering the Colorado won an Academy Award nomination for short subjects in 1939.
Burg extended his travels around the world aboard the yacht, Camargo, 1931-1932, and followed up in 1933-1934 with a trip in a small boat around Cape Horn. Filmmaking for ERPI and Encyclopaedia Britannica subsequently took him throughout the western United States, Central and South America, Alaska, Europe, and Asia.
In the early 1950s, Burg settled down in Alaska, working forst for the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, and then establishing himself with the Alaska Department of Fish and Game, 1955-1974. He established the department's Information and Education Section and made many films as part of his work. He also made the Alaska Centennial film, Juneau, Alaska's Capital City. He continued to make many river trips well after his retirement. He died in Alaska in 1985, and his ashes have since been scattered on many of the rivers he voyaged.
The collection documents not only Burg's life, adventures, work, and family, but also traces his development as a photographer, from teenage years, when he took snapshots of his sea voyages around the world, to the late 1920s, when he started producing photographs that graced the pages of glossy magazines such as National Geographic and films for Encyclopaedia Brittanica Films and ERPI Classroom Films. He became an expert at taking shots of people, and his photography of children is particularly striking. The collection includes prints, negatives, slides, and lantern slides. Amos Burg appears in many photographs throughout the collection.
The collection is organized into the following subgroups and series:
Subgroup 1: Amos Burg, His Family, and His Travels, 1889-1950
Series A: Family, Early Life, and College, 1889-circa 1935
Series B: Seaman, 1918-1927
Series C: Adventurer/Lecturer/Writer, 1920-1950
Subgroup 2: Amos Burg, Alaskan, 1951-1985
NOTE: This guide describes Subgroup 1 only. Subgroup 2 will be added when processing is complete.
The collection is open to the public.
Library accession nos. 17787, 18819, 19839, 20170, 22211, 22726, and 24251.
Manuscript materials were separated into the Amos Burg Papers (Mss 1759) in the Manuscripts Collection at the Oregon Historical Society Research Library. Film is in the Amos Burg Motion Picture Collection (Mic 5).
Fleischmann, Julius. Footsteps in the Sea. New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1935.
Amos Burg's photographs appeared with articles written by him and others in National Geographic.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Burg, Amos--Photographs.
Burg family--Photographs.
McCormick Steamship Co.; Encyclopaedia Britannica Films, Inc.; Erpi Classroom Films, Inc.
Alaska--Description and travel.; British Isles--Description and travel.; Cape Horn (Chile)--Description and travel.; Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico)--Description and travel.; Columbia River--Description and travel.; Indonesia--Description and travel.; Mackenzie River (N.W.T.)--Description and travel.; Magdalena River (Columbia)--Description and travel.; Nunivak Island (Alaska)--Description and travel.; Oregon--Description and travel.; Salmon River (Idaho)--Description and travel.; Scandinavia--Description and travel.; Snake River (Idaho)--Description and travel.; Spain--Description and travel.; Thailand--Description and travel.; West Indies--Description and travel.; West (U.S.)--Description and travel.; Yukon River (Yukon and Alaska)--Description and travel.
Boats and boating; Canoes and canoeing; Eskimos.; Fishing--Alaska.
Alaska; Idaho; Montana; Oregon; Washington (State); Photographs; Environmental Conditions; Fisheries and Wildlife; Sports and Recreation; Transportation
Negatives.; Photograph albums.; Photographic prints.
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Amos Burg, His Family, and His Adventures, 1889-1950; Subgroup 1
  This Subgroup is organized into three series:
  SeriesA: Family, Early Life, and College, 1889-ca. 1935
  Series B: Seaman, 1918-1927
  Series C: Adventures, Expeditions, and Freelance Projects, 1920-1950
  - Family and Early Life, 1889-circa 1935; Series A; 161 photographs and 21 photomechanical prints.
    Includes the Burg family, early photographs of Amos Burg, Jr., the Burg home, family friends, the City Laundry and other Portland area locations and activities. It also includes mages from Burg's various stints at the University of Oregon and possibly Oregon State. (See timeline in this guide for details.)
    - Burg family, 1889-circa 1935 (Box-folder 1/1)
      Includes Amos, Sr., and Annie Laurie Burg; their children, Amos, Jr., Carrie [Edwards], Charles W., George W., John E., Mabel A.H. [Merryman], [Mrs. Ellery Reim], and Vera B. [Yunker]; and grandchildren, including Anna Rose. Also included is a biographical sketch of Mr. and Mrs. Burg, Sr.
    - Amos Burg, Jr., circa 1915-circa 1925 (Box-folder 1/2, Box-folder 2/6)
      Includes one image with camera, formal portraits and snapshots. Two images show him in canoe, probably on Columbia River in Portland area. Album 450-3: Burg (with crutch) and group of friends or relatives (pg. 56); in plaid jacket and tie (pg. 92).
    - Burg friends and relatives--formal portraits, circa 1905-1930 (Box-folder 1/3)
      Unidentified young men and one young woman. One portrait of a scout troop is inscribed to Burg "from his Scoutmaster Bert V. Chappel, 2/4/1930."
    - Burg friends and relatives--snapshots, identified, circa 1915-1928 (Box-folder 1/4, Box-folder 2/5, 2/7)
      Identified people in loose snapshots include: Frieda and "Grandma" Gibcke, Etta Gray, Aaron Loughey, Carolyn and Gertrude Schail, Bernice [?], Josie [?], Lillian [?], and Vivian [?]. Identified people in Album 450-3: Tommy and Jennie (pg. 1); LaWanda, Edith, Claudia, Alice, Mary (Pg. 73); Tommy (pg. 92).
    - Burg friends and relatives--snapshots, unidentified, circa 1910-1920 (Box-folder 1/5, Box-folder 2/6)
      Album 450-3: girl with dog, two girls wearing jodphurs (pg. 48); children, including girl with dog (pg. 58); others (pg. 73, 92).
    - Burg friends and relatives--snapshots, with animals, automobiles, houses, at various locations, circa 1910-1920 (Box-folder 1/6)
      Identified people include: Frieda and "Grandma" Gibcke, Etta Gray, Aaron Loughey, Carolyn and Gertrude Schail, Bernice [?], Josie [?], Lillian [?], Vivian [?].
    - Oregon locations--Eastern, 1919 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Oregon locations--Portland, circa 1925 (Box-folder 1/8, Box-folder 2/6)
      Rose Festival parade floats. In Album 450-3 (p. 34-35) are floats, including the State Laundry float, with a shirt collar and laundry on a clothesline cleverly rendered in flowers.
    - Oregon locations--unidentfied, circa 1925 (Box-folder 2/5-6)
      Album 450-3: images in snow-covered forested countryside (pg. 35-37), including photographer shooting with tripod-mounted camera (back to camera, possibly Burg) and unusual round-tracked vehicle pulling wooden bus on sled.
    - University of Orego, 1926-1929; 1931 (Box-folder 1/9, Box-folder 2/6)
      Includes portrait of Amos Burg, associate editor, with staff of the Emerald, University of Oregon student daily newspaper. Other staff members identified: Dorothy Baker, Melvin Cohn, William Haggerty, Leonard Hagstrom, Donald Johnston, Arden X. Pangborn, Joe Pigney, and Arthur Schoeni. Images also include Burg in a typing class, as well as individual and group shots of classmates. Also included is a group portrait that includes Burg, dated 1931, when he returned to campus, probably to give a lecture. Album 450-3: group portrait (pg. 56).
    - University of Oregon--Plane trip from Eugene Airport, 1927-1929 (Box-folder 1/10)
      Photographs taken at the airport as Burg was preparing to depart with pilot David Langmack to photograph the Three Sisters peaks for a newsreel. Includes photocopy of Burg's account from the Emerald.
    - Postcards collected and sent by Burg, 1921, undated (Box-folder 1/11)
      Includes postcard folder, "The Shasta Route," sent to his mother in Portland from the "Summit Siskiyou Range".
  - Seaman, 1918-1927; Series B; 520 photographs and 64 photomechanical prints.
    Images document ships, crews, life and work aboard ship, and ports of call, most notably in Japan and China. The series include a number of photographs of Amos Burg. The bulk of the photographs of his merchant seaman career are contained in three photograph albums. Album 450-1 includes his first voyages from 1918-1920. He may not have had a camera until he shipped on the SS Katia in September 1918, so voyages before that time are documented by postcards and other photomechanical prints and a teenager's purple prose. Most of Burg's photographs in this album document his voyage aboard the Katia on the Northern Circle route to Japan and on to other Asian ports, then through the Indian Ocean and Suez Canal to Marseilles, France. The 2.5-inch by 3.5-inch prints are fading, but they give a hint of the photographic strengths and skills Burg would develop, particularly in photographing people. Album 450-2 includes good quality prints by Burg of his voyage aboard the SS President Madison in 1923, and Album 450-3 (which also includes expeditions and other trips in Series C) includes a few images from several voyages but mostly good quality prints from his voyage aboard the President Jackson.
    - SS Lurline--San Francisco to Hawaii, 1918 January (Box-folder 2/2)
      Postcard print of ship (Album 450-1, pg. 49)
    - SS Ventura--San Francisco to Hawaii, Pago Pago, Samoa, and Sydney, Australia, 1918 May 28-July 5 (Box-folder 2/1-2)
      Burg shipped as bridge cadet. Album 450-1: 29 postcard and photomechanical prints, pgs. 9-10, 23, 28-29, 51, 75.
    - SS Katia--Seattle to Marseille, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 1/12, Box-folder 2/1-3)
      Many photographs of the voyage are in Album 450-1 (Box 2/Folders 1-3). Locations include Dutch Harbor and Unalaska, Alaska; Siberia; Kobe and Yokohama, Japan; Shanghai; Saigon; Singapore; Rangoon; Colombo; and Suez Canal and Port Said, Egypt. Burg won promotion to able seaman at Kobe.
    - SS Patria--Marseille to New York via Oran, Algeria, 1919 June (Box-folder 2/1-3)
      French transport carrying 2,500 American troops. Album 450-1: 7 photographic prints and 9 photomechanical prints, pgs. 12-13, 35-36, 45, 59-61, 73, 82, and 95.
    - SS Matsonnia--San Francisco via Honolulu, Hawaii, 1919 (Box-folder 1/13, Box-folder 2/2)
      Images of Honolulu and Waikiki beach. Ship photo in Album 450-1 (pg. 49). Burg was bridge cadet.
    - SS Wakiki--New York to Manchester, England, via Panama and the Azores, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1/14, Box-folder 2/2)
      Images include scenes in Panama and off-loading lumber at Manchester. One print in Album 450-1 (pg. 63)
    - SS Lapland--Southampton, England, to New York, 1920 (Box-folder 1/15)
      After SS Waikiki was rammed and badly damaged by the SS Cape Transport, the Waikiki crew returned to New York on the Lapland
    - SS Egeria--Portland to Sydney and Newcastle, Australia, and return, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 1/16, Box-folder 2/7)
      Includes postcard print Burg sent from Hawaii to his sister, Mabel, in Portland. Tw views of Honolulu harbor in Album 450-3 (pg. 76)
    - SS West Kader--San Francisco to Yokohama, Nagoya, and Kobe, Japan, and Shanghai, 1922 (Box-folder 1/17)
      Burg, who shipped as able seaman, was hospitalized for a month at Shanghai after injuring knee at Kobe.
    - SS Hanna Nielsen--Shanghai via Tsingtao to Astoria, 1922 (Box-folder 1/18, Box-folder 2/7)
      Burg returned with first load of goods to start his import business. Includes views of Tsingtaoand photos of ship's crew. One view of Tsingtao in Album 450-3 (pg. 76).
    - SS President Madison--To Japan, China, and the Philippines, 1923 (Box-folder 1/19, Box-folder 2/4)
      Burg shipped as quartermaster on another buying trip for his import business. All of Album 450-2 (2/4) are photos Burg made of this trip or commercially-produced postcards and other prints of life in China and the Philippines. Also includes views of SS President McKinley and crew.
    - SS President Jackson--To Japan, China, Hong Kong, and the Philippines, 1927 (Box-folder 1/20, Box-folder 2/5-7)
      Burg shipped as able seaman on another buying trip for his import business. Good photographs of the ship (especially with iced-up rigging on the "Northern Circle") and its crew, underway, in dry dock in Yokohama, Japan, and of several harbors. Many photographs are in 450-3 (pg. 1-2, 10-12, 19, 28-33, 48, 64-71, 96-97, and 102).
    - SS President Jackson[?]--Kuomintang conflict [?], 1927 (Box-folder 1/21, Box-folder 2/5-7)
      Three mounted prints of executions in China, possibly during Kuomintang drive to capture Beijing, probably obtained by Burg in China.
    - Seaman--prints on album pages, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 1/22)
      Includes black-and-white prints of voyages on SS Katia, SS Wakiki, and SS Lapland, and photomechanical prints of ships, including SS Queen, and the harbor at Yokohama, Japan.
    - Seaman--loose and prints, unidentified, 1918-circa 1923 (Box-folder 1/23)
      Album 450-3: pavilion-like building (pg. 49), girl riding ostriche (pg. 52)
  - Adventurer/Lecturer/Writer, 1920-1950; Series C
    The series is arranged into 37 subseries that follow approximately chronologically Amos Burg's path around the world. Subseries 37 includes a small quantity of photographs by other photographers that Burg obtained from various sources.
    - Amos Burg, His Boats, and His Friends and Photo Subjects, circa 1925-1945; Subseries 1; 207 photographs and 64 photomechanical prints.
      - Amos Burg--snapshot size images, circa 1930-circa 1945 (Box-folder 3/1)
        Includes one image of Burg holding 35-mm camera and many of him aboard boats.
      - Amos Burg--5x7-inch and larger images, circa 1930-circa 1945 (Box-folder 3/2)
        Includes one image of Burg with Walter W. Hoffman (Spike), inscribed on verso to Burg and one with South Seas women from the Camargo voyage.
      - Amos Burg--lecture promotion images, circa 1930-circa 1940 (Box-folder 3/3)
        From lecture tours on Columbia and Snake River canoe trips, the Camargo voyage, the Cape Horn expedition, and Alaska trips.
      - Boat, Dorjun, 1933-circa 1945 (Box-folder 3/4)
        Includes views during renovation of the former Coast Guard vessel and its christening by Dorette Fleischmann, who named it Dorjun in honor of her two children, Dorothy and Junior (Charles Fleischman III). Also includes later images in Alaska and the Portland area.
      - Boat, Endeavor, circa 1930-circa 1945 (Box-folder 3/5)
        Includes views when it belonged to Capt. Oliver P. Rankin of Astoria and after Rankin turned the boat over to hsi friend, Amos Burg, in 1938. Folder includes printout of Web site created by Fritz Funk, owner of the Endeavor as of 2004.
      - Friends, photo subjects, etc.--identified, A-J, circa 1925-circa 1945 (Box-folder 3/6)
        Alice [?], Margaret Bayne, J. Barry (with KVOA microphone), Anne Bergstrand, [Mr. and Mrs.] Gwludys Bowen, the Most Reverend Bartholomew Cattaneo (including card honoring his consecration to the Episcopacy, St. Patrick's Church, Sydney, Australia), Dr. Arthur L. Canfield, L. Chamnanvitya, Dan [?], Trevor Davis, Jo [?] (and Nelly [?] ).
      - Friends, photo subjects, etc.--identified, L-T, circa 1930-circa 1940 (Box-folder 3/7)
        Capt. Alfred Larsen (and wife), Merl LaVoy, Fred and Laura Lockley, [?] Long, Ward Randall, Rita [?], Bertha Schwan, Jesse and Joy Sill (their house, not them), Eugene M. Tardy (in Indian headress with child in Indian dress), Donald H. Thompson, and Clara and Doris Tobin with Amos Burg's dog, King (one image used as Christmas card for Emory, Doris and Clara Tobin).
      - Friends, photo subjects, etc.--unidentified--children, circa 1925-circa 1945 (Box-folder 3/8)
      - Friends, photo subjects, etc.--unidentified--groups, circa 1925-circa 1945 (Box-folder 3/9)
      - Friends, photo subjects, etc.--unidentified--men, circa 1925-circa 1945 (Box-folder 3/10)
      - Friends, photo subjects, etc.--unidentified--women, circa 1930-circa 1945 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - New York to Northwest Train Trip, 1920; Subseries 2; 20 photographs.
      - New York sightseeing, 1920 (Box-folder 3/12)
      - On Northern Pacific--St. Paul, Minn., to Spokane, Wash., 1920 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Canoe trip--Snake River at Lewiston, Idaho, to mouth of Columbia River, 1920 May-June; Subseries 3; 101 photographs.
      Trip with Fred Hill (Spoke) of Spokane, Wash., who had been Burg's shipmate on the Wakiki.
      - Train trip to Lewiston, Idaho, 1920 May 24 (Box-folder 3/14)
      - Lewiston, Idaho, to Indian, 1920 May 25 (Box-folder 3/15)
      - Indian to Central Ferry, 1920 May 26-27 (Box-folder 3/16)
      - Riparia to Umatilla area, 1920 May 28-31 (Box-folder 3/17)
      - John Day to Deschutes, 1920 June 2-3 (Box-folder 3/18)
      - Celilo to Dalles-Celilo Canal, 1920 June 4-5 (Box-folder 3/19)
      - Mosier area to Cascades, 1920 June 6-9 (Box-folder 3/20)
      - Lower Columbia River, 1920 June 12-15 (Box-folder 3/21)
      - Unidentified, undated, 1920 May-June (Box-folder 3/22, Box-folder 2/5)
        One Columbia River view in Album 450-3 (pg. 16).
    - Canoe trip--Yellowstone, Missouri and Mississippi [Livingston, Mt., to New Orleans, La.], 1922; Subseries 4; 145 photographs.
      While serving as a seaman aboard the SS West Kader to Japan and back in early 1922, Burg started studying up on early voyageurs, including Lewis and Clark. In June, he shipped his canoe by rail to Livingston, Montana, and started down the Yellowstone River to St. Louis on the Missouri. He then canoed on down the Mississippi River to New Orleans. He returned to Portland as banana messenger (his job was to keep the bananas ventilated so they didn't ripen too soon) on the Pacific Fruit Express train.
      - Yellowstone and Missouri to St. Louis, 1922 (Box-folder 4/1, Box-folder 2/7)
        Album 450-3 (2/7): p. 78.
      - Mississippi River, 1922
        - Burg and his canoe, 1922 (Box-folder 4/2, Box-folder 2/7)
        - Cities and towns, 1922 (Box-folder 4/3)
        - Levees and bridge, 1922 (Box-folder 4/4)
        - People, 1922 (Box-folder 4/5, Box-folder 2/7)
        - River scenes, 1922 (Box-folder 4/6)
        - Ships, 1922 (Box-folder 4/7)
        - Steamboats, 1922 (Box-folder 4/8)
        - Steamboats--crew members, 1922 (Box-folder 4/9)
        - Steamboats-- Kate Adams (Memphis to Greenville), 1922 (Box-folder 4/10)
        - Steamboats--snag boats, 1922 (Box-folder 4/11)
        - Other boats, 1922 (Box-folder 4/12)
        - Vicksburg--Civil War battlefield, 1922 (Box-folder 4/13, Box-folder 2/7)
        - Pacific Fruit Express train, 1922 (Box-folder 4/14, Box-folder 2/7)
      - Yellowstone and Missouri to St. Louis--unidentified images, 1922 (Box-folder 4/15)
    - Canoe trip--Columbia River from source to mouth, 1924-1925; Subseries 5; 56 photographs.
      - Amos Burg and his canoe, Song o' the Winds, 1924 (Box-folder 4/16)
      - People, places, and activities, 1924 (Box-folder 4/17)
      - River scenes, 1924
        - Identified locations--British Columbia, 1924 (Box-folder 4/18, Box-folder 2/6)
          Album 450-3 (2/6) includes 21-Mile Rapids, Canoe River, Donald Canyon, Kinbasket Lake, and Ed Robinson's cabin at 12-Mile (pgs. 40, 42-43), hotel near Revelstoke and other scenes (p. 60)
        - Identified locations--Washington state, 1924 (Box-folder 4/19, Box-folder 2/5, 2/7)
          Album 450-3 includes Burg and canoe at mouth of Walla Walla River (pg. 16), Little Dalles (p. 80).
        - Unidentified locations, 1924 (Box-folder 4/20-21, Box-folder 2/5)
          Images also in Album 450-3 (2/5), pp. 21-23, 26
      - Newspaper photograph layout, 1924 (Box-folder 4/22)
      - Photographs by "P.W.C." [unidentified photographer], 1924 (Box-folder 4/23, Box-folder 2/5, 2/7)
        Album 450-3 includes images by P.W.C. (pgs. 20, 26-27, 80)